Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Political Science Records, 1956-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Political Science Records, 1956-2014
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Dept. of Political Science
UWM Archival Collection 108
5.6 cubic ft. (10 boxes) 118 digital text files (14 MB)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Records of the Department of Political Science, including course syllabi, correspondence, staff meeting minutes, and miscellaneous information on lectures, undergraduate and graduate programs, and department seminars. A large portion of the collection is devoted to the development and organization of a Law Studies Program within the Dept. of Political Science.
The Dept. of Political Science was established in 1956 when the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee was created. The Dept. of Political Science instituted a master of science program in 1959, and a doctoral program in 1967.
Department Chairs
1956-1958 Charles D. Goff
1958-1961 Donald R. Shea
1961-1965 Marvin R. Summers
1965-1969 Wilder W. Crane, Jr.
1969-1972 Cornelius P. Cotter
1972-1976 John F. Bibby
1976-1979 Mark Tessler
1979-1982 Brett Hawkins
1982-1986 Meredith Watts
1986-1989 Howard Handelman
1989-1992 Stephan Percy
1992-1994 Ronald Weber
1994-1996 Meredith Watts
1996-2002 Marcus Ethridge
2002-2005 Howard Handelman
2005-2010 Marcus Ethridge
2010-2014 Tom Holbrook
2014- Kathleen Dolan
Records of the chair of the Department of Political Science, as well as files from the office as a whole. The correspondence files largely consist of letters between the dean and associate dean of the College of Letters & Science and the chair of the Dept. of Political Science regarding budgets, staffing, program development, events, and curricula.
Much of the collection pertains to the development of a Law Studies Program within the Political Science department. Included with the Law Studies materials are NEH Grant reports, consultation reports, budgets, correspondence, curricula, and other records of the Law Studies coordinator. The collection also contains materials on a Washington D.C. internship coordinated by the Dept. of Political Science and information regarding the Political Research Laboratory. Also included are course syllabi, minutes of various committees, documentation of graduate programs, information about the student strike of 1970, and correspondence of the Joint Conference Committee of the Political Science Departments of UW-Madison and UW-Milwaukee (1957-1963).
The collection also includes course syllabi from courses offered by the Department from 1988-2014. Many of the paper syllabi folders (1988-2010) also contain blank copies of midterm and final exams from the courses to which they pertain; such folders are labeled in the boxes, and the exams are provided for pedagogical study purposes.
This collection was received in multiple parts. Additional materials have been physically arranged and intellectually arranged and interfiled, but researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
The collection is organized alphabetically by subject, and thereunder chronologically. Syllabi files in Boxes 8-10 are organized by course number. The electronic syllabi are organized by academic year; file names include the course number and instructor for that semester's offering of the course.
An inventory/database of the Electronic Records is available in the Archives. Contact an archivist for more information.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
Administrative/Restriction Information
Folders 22 and 24 in box 8 are restricted in accordance with the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 (FERPA). Folders will be removed before presenting the box to researchers. Contact an archivist for more information.
The records in box 3, as well as folders 6-9 in box 8, are restricted in accordance with UWM Personnel File Policy S-42. Access is regulated by Section III. A.2 and III. A.3.
Electronic records must be accessed at computers in the Archives. Contact an archivist for more information.
There are no access restrictions on the rest of the collection, which is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown donor transferred the collection to the Archives prior to 1989. Electronic Records were transferred to the Archives in Fall of 2010, Spring of 2012, and Winter of 2013 from the Dept. of Political Science (Accessions 2010-030, 2011-034, 2012-027, and 2012-046). The Department of Political Science donated additional materials in July 2010 (accessions 2010-004 and 2010-008) and in September 2010 (accession 2010-016).
As of November 2012 all files were accessible on a computer running Windows XP Professional Version 2002, with Service Pack 3. Adobe Reader 9 was used to read the files.
The collection includes the following file formats:
Acrobat PDF versions 1.3 - 1.6 [.pdf]
Contents List
- Records, 1956-2014, UWM Archival Collection 108; 5.6 cubic ft. (10 boxes) 118 digital text files (14 MB)
  - Agreement Between Political Science and Global Studies, 1999-2009 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Audit and Review, 1985-1995 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Center for International Studies, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Civil Libertarian Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Community Relations Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3-7)
    - 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1961-1978 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Department Sponsored Lectures, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Departmental Staff Meetings, 1956-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
  - Doctorate Program Assessment, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Enrollment Statistics, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee, Minutes and Correspondence
    - 1956-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
      Restricted
    - 1989-1999 (Box 8, Folder 6-9)
  - Faculty Research Reports, 1989-1994 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Full Professors' Meeting, 1966-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Committee, 1970-1976 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
  - Graduate Program Policies, Admission Check List and Brochure, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Graduate Program Review
    - 1984-2007 (Box 8, Folder 12-17)
    - Consultant's Report, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Graduate Programs, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Honorary Degrees Program, 1992-2000 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Joint Conference Committee, 1957-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Law Studies Program
    - 1989-1992 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Annual Reports, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Budget Revisions, 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Consultancy Grant, Report and Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Consultants' Site Visit, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Curricula and Syllabi, 1975-1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Grant Extension Request, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Guest Lectures, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Implementation Grant, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Conference, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Pilot Grant, Report and Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Program Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Transfer to Political Science, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Library and Research Aids Committee, 1958-1973 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mock Trial
    - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Teams, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - National Defense Education Act Master's Program Grant Application, 1958-1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Pi Sigma Alpha, Membership Lists and Correspondence, 1970-1995 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Political Research Laboratory, 1967-1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Political Science News, vol. 2 issue 2, 1977 (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Program Array Review, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Program Reviews and Correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Proposals, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Student Opinion Polls, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Student Strike, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Self-Study, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Syllabi
    - 1988-2010
      - Course Numbers 103-193 (Box 8, Folder 29-39)
      - Course Numbers 203-390 (Box 9, Folder 1-29)
      - Course Numbers 396-974, 921-001 (Box 10, Folder 1-30)
    - 2010-2014
  - Taft Seminar, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Teacher Certification in Political Science, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Undergraduate Committee, Minutes and Correspondence, 1986-1998 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Undergraduate Curriculum, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Undergraduate Internships, 1998-2006 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Undergraduate Program Audit and Review, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - United Nations' Summer Seminar, 1965-1974 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Washington Center for Learning Alternatives Newsletters, Brochures, and Announcements, 1982-1987 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Washington Internship, 1976-1987 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Washington Seminar, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)